I've failed you.
是我办事不力
I couldn't kill Shen Du in Yingzhou.
未在营州拿下沈渡
Have all sect members in Yingzhou
营州的火蛾门
been completely wiped out?
全没有了
Yes...
是
Trash
废物
has no place here!
不可留
You're in bad shape.
伤得不轻
You'll take time to get in fighting form.
看来是要养些时日了
Have you delt with
营州的那些半面鬼
those masked spectres in Yingzhou?
可都有处理好
Poison was planted beforehand.
已经事先种下了毒
There will be no survivors!
绝无活口
Very good.
很好
What about the item
那莫谦之
left for Shen Du by Mo Qianzhi?
留给沈渡的东西呢
This is it.
这就是沈渡要找的东西
Mo Qianzhi
这个莫谦之
has been in charge of Yingzhou for so long,
盯着营州那么久
He probably had the dirt on
想必是掌握了
numerous officials.
不少朝中人的把柄
A poetry collection?
诗集
How could that be?
怎么会
It must have been switched by
一定是那个时候
Shen Du back then!
被沈渡调了包
You were tricked by Shen Du!
你被沈渡给耍了
I...
我
[Shen Du,]
沈渡
[I'm eager to witness]
我倒要看看
your next move in this game.
你接下来要如何破局
I didn't expect
没想到
Lord Zhang's faction has been
张相党羽这么多年
smuggling with Xichen
一直通过甘南道
through Gannan for so many years,
同西辰国走私往来
making huge profits.
获取暴利
Princess Ying is cunningly
英王殿下
using funding as a cover to win
竟然也以资助为名
the loyalty of the troops at the border.
收买边陲将士人心
Qianzhi had quietly gathered
师兄默默掌握了
compromising information on two factions
朝中两股势力的把柄
but hadn't reported it.
却未曾上报
It seems he didn't trust the imperial court.
想来是不相信朝廷
Chen Huo'e must be aware of some details,
陈火蛾应该是知晓一二
which is why she intended on using
所以想借我的手
my resources to locate this booklet.
找到这本册子
So, what's your plan for the next move?
那你要如何处理这个
I think...
我想
[Lord Shen!]
大阁领
Lord Shen, we have a situation!
大阁领 不好了
Why the panic?
何事慌乱
The masked spectres we captured
抓到的几个半面鬼
haven't disclosed anything
还没问出什么
before they all suddenly died.
就都暴毙了
My lord, these individuals
禀大阁领
[must have succumbed to poisoning.]
这些人应是中毒身亡
[When they were brought in,]
他们被抓进来的时候
[I conducted a thorough search,]
我仔细地搜过身
[even inspecting their mouths]
就连嘴巴里的牙齿
[to check their teeth.]
都一一检查过
There was absolutely no chance
绝不可能有
for them to have poisoned themselves.
让他们服毒的机会
The needle mark...
这针眼
So this is...
怎么会
Have you discovered anything?
是有什么发现
Jing Lin was right.
景林说得没错
These spectres must have been poisoned
这些人被抓进来之前
by some form of chronic toxin
应该是中了
before they were brought in.
某种慢性毒药
Could you identify
仵作可否查出
what type of poison it is?
是何种毒药
Absolutely.
可以
However, it will require some time.
不过需要一些时日
Report once you have confirmation.
查明之后立刻上报
[Understood, my lord.]
是 大阁领
Time for us to return to Xiang'an.
是时候回襄安了
What are you reading?
你在看什么
Throughout our journey,
这一路上
we've passed
我们沿途
through numerous places,
经过了不少地方
and these
这些
are my notes
是我与当地百姓
from interaction with the locals.
闲聊的记录
Did you uncover anything noteworthy?
是有什么不同的发现吗
From their recollections,
从这些人的回忆中
I did stumble upon something intriguing.
确实是发现了一点蹊跷
The year prior to the Shens' incident,
沈府旧案发生的前一年
the empire experienced severe flooding.
大苍遭遇了水患
Many people endured great hardship
不少百姓因为粮食短缺
due to food shortages.
而过得极度困难
However, here in Gannan
可在甘南道这里
the locals' memories
百姓的记忆中
indicate that some areas
也有一些地区
were indeed affected by the floods.
受了水灾的影响
Logically speaking,
按理来说
there should have been a food shortage.
应该余粮不足才对
Yet the grain prices not only didn't
可当地的粮价
rise but actually dropped significantly.
非但没涨反而降了不少
Where did this seemingly abundant
这些凭空出现的粮食
grain come from?
究竟从何而来
Are you implying that...
你的意思是说
There is indeed a possibility
的确有一种可能
that someone secretly took the
有人暗中
public grain from the official granaries.
取走了粮仓中的官粮
[Assassins!]
有刺客
[Xing.]
六娘
Let's go!
走
No need to get caught up in battle.
不必恋战
Let's head to the palace!
我们进宫
Lord Shen treats the empire like his own family.
沈大人果然忧国如家
[You've barely set foot in the capital,]
这刚入皇城
[and already you're here to report in.]
就来宫中禀报
No wonder my mother
难怪我母后
holds you in such high esteem.
会如此器重于你
Princess Ying, I'm flattered.
英王殿下过誉了
I'm simply doing my utmost
臣不过是尽己所能
to honor the trust
但求不负
placed in me by Her Majesty.
太皇太后的信任
If you truly mean it,
你若当真有此意念
splendid.
最好
It would honor my mother's
也不枉我母后
thoughtful regard for you.
对你一番思量
May you soar to great heights.
望你扶摇而上
What do you mean by that, Your Highness?
殿下此言何意
Never mind.
罢了
It's getting late tonight.
今夜已深
My darling must be tired as well, right?
嘉安也累了吧
Shen Du, let's continue
沈渡
our conversation when you visit me later.
回头来我府上再叙吧
Your Majesty, please have some tea.
太皇太后 您喝茶
[Your Majesty,]
太皇太后
they have arrived.
他们来了
Greetings, Your Majesty.
给太皇太后请安
May you be graced with eternal well-being.
太皇太后万福金安
You may rise.
起来吧
[Lord Shen,]
沈爱卿啊
I've already reviewed
你派人送来的奏折
the report you submitted.
哀家已经看过了
[Mo Qianzhi is dead.]
莫谦之已死
[The rebels have been eliminated,]
叛军已剿
and the spectres have been wiped out.
半面鬼也被歼灭了
[Your actions in Yingzhou were commendable.]
营州一事办得不错
During your investigation,
在办案中
have you encountered any challenges?
还遇到过什么难处啊
By the grace of Your Majesty,
托太皇太后洪福
all had been well.
一切顺利
What reward should I bestow upon you,
哀家得赏些什么
my lord?
给爱卿呢
Shen Du is already the head of
这沈渡本就是大内阁领
Imperial Guard, overseeing officials at
统领各级官员
[all levels, and holds a top rank title.]
已是一品大员了
So his position
那这官岂不是
doesn't leave much room for advancement.
无甚可升了
[You certainly have a way with words!]
你这张嘴
It's my high esteem for you
皆是哀家宠你
that allows you to speak so freely!
信口开河
Fortunately,
幸好
Lord Shen is a confidant.
沈爱卿不是外人
[Otherwise,]
否则
[it might give the impression]
会让人觉得
that I want to use your tongue
哀家想借你的嘴
to reprimand Lord Shen.
敲打沈爱卿不成
Apologies, Your Majesty,
太皇太后恕罪
Baohuan acknowledges my mistake.
宝环知错了
Lord Shen,
沈爱卿啊
[what are your thoughts?]
你作何想啊
What reward do you desire?
你想要什么赏赐
Feel free to tell me.
尽管跟哀家说
I will certainly grant it.
我定会答应的
Those were all but my duty as a subject;
这本就是臣的分内之事
no reward is necessary.
无须赏赐
Regarding the mission in Yingzhou,
此次营州之行
if it weren't for my lady by my side,
若不是有夫人在侧
It likely wouldn't have gone so smoothly.
恐怕也不会如此顺利
If there's to be a reward,
若要赏赐
it should go to Yan Xing, the scribe.
都官令史颜幸当赏
So you are
原来
seeking a reward for your own lady.
是要为自家夫人讨赏呢
[It seems this task in Yingzhou]
看来这营州之行
has deepened the bond between you two.
你们夫妻感情精进
I've truly done a good deed!
哀家可是做了件好事啊
Gratitude, Your Majesty.
太皇太后英明
[Please rise.]
起来吧
Lord Shen is truly a pillar of the state,
沈爱卿实乃肱股之臣
achieving greatness without seeking credit.
功成不居啊
Very well.
好
As for the rewards,
这赏赐的事
I will honor your wishes
就依了你
and grant them to your wife.
给阁领夫人了
For her meritorious service in quelling the rebels,
颜爱卿平营州之乱有功
Lady Yan is promoted to the Chief Clerk
擢升刑部辖下都官主事
under the Ministry of Justice, rank six, junior grade.
从六品
Gratitude, Your Majesty.
谢太皇太后
[Lady Yan,]
颜爱卿啊
is there anything else
你还有什么
you particularly seek as a reward?
特殊想要的赏赐啊
Your Majesty,
回太皇太后
I have no other
微臣并无
wishes for rewards.
其他想要的赏赐
You should think carefully;
你可要想好了
this is a rare opportunity.
机会难得的
My words are all sincere.
微臣所言句句属实
I seek no reward,
微臣不想要赏赐
only a peaceful and just world.
唯愿天下清明太平
Commendable!
好
[Lady Yan,]
颜爱卿
[despite being a woman,]
身为女子
[your heart is with the empire.]
心系天下
Our empire needs
我们大苍
more officials
真是需要
with your spirit.
颜爱卿这样的官员
I heard you faced a
听说你们在营州时
dire crisis in Yingzhou
遭遇劫难
and nearly lost your lives.
差点丧命
[Send for the imperial healer to attend to you.]
着御医去府上调理
[Yes, Your Royal Highness.]
是
What's bothering you?
怎么了
Why do you look so downcast
才得了赏赐
after receiving a promotion?
为何闷闷不乐的
Congratulations, Chief Clerk!
都官颜主事
I just started to piece it together.
我这才刚咂摸过味儿来
Our achievement is quite significant.
营州之行兹事体大
Her Majesty wouldn't want to appear ungrateful,
太皇太后不赏不好看
but she also doesn't want to reward you.
可又并不想赏你
Zhang Baohuan
那个张宝环
must have seen through
定是看懂了
her intentions
太皇太后的心思
and colluded with Lady Xu.
与徐内司唱起了双簧
They claimed there's nothing to reward,
故意说什么封无可封
just to prevent you from taking credit.
就是不想你邀功
If it weren't for your cunning move
若不是你精明求全
to get past the subject,
将此事揭了过去
who knows what might have happened.
还真保不齐会怎样
What about the booklet
莫大人留给你
that Lord Mo left for you?
那本册子
How do you plan to deal with it?
你要如何处理
That booklet involves many parties.
那本册子牵连甚广
I'll seize the right moment to unveil it.
待日后找机会呈上吧
You're sharper than a fox!
狐狸都精不过你
You entered the palace at night
你连夜进宫
to debrief Her Majesty
求见太皇太后
but didn't mention the booklet,
却又不提册子的事
just to keep some officials guessing.
就是为了虚晃一招
This way, some people will be on edge,
好让有些人心生忌惮
and they probably won't
恐怕他们
get a good night sleep.
今晚都睡不安稳了
My lady is the one who
知我者
truly understands me.
夫人也
So, you did
所以
all the work, yet I claimed the credit.
我这是躺着捡了个封赏
Princess Ying praised your dedication,
英王殿下说你忠于职守
but surely you don't need to
但你也不用
be so dedicated that
半夜都忠于职守
you stay up all night?
不回家吧
There's some place
有个地方
I would like you, my lady, to see.
我得让夫人知道
Let's go.
走
What is this...
这是
Here's something I'd like
这是我要让夫人
you to know.
知道的事
Years ago, the Shen Family faced disaster,
当年沈家遇难
and my mother fell gravely ill.
我娘身染重病
Knowing her time was short,
自知命不久矣
she had me write a confession.
便让我写了自白书
I don't know how.
我不会写
I also shouldn't.
我也不能写
Father preferred death
父亲
over living with a tarnished name.
宁愿用死来证明清白
I prefer to die nobly,
我宁愿同父亲一样
as my father would.
以死明志
But if you die too,
可要是连你都死了
then this injustice
那这冤案
will truly be buried forever.
可就真的结了
The countless
沈家
wrongful deaths
上上下下
in the Shen Family,
这么多枉死的人
including your father,
还有你爹
their grievances,
他们的冤屈
and the truth they always sought
他们一直想要的真相
will remain unknown forever!
可就真的没有人知道了
[She also advised me to endure for]
还劝诫我
[a while, then enter public service,]
说忍一时入仕
[so I would have the chance]
方才有机会
[to restore the Shen Family's honor.]
还沈家一世清白
From that day on,
从那日起
my life
我此生
has been lived solely for revenge.
唯有为恨而活了
I carry on my shoulders the
我身上背负着
grievances of many Shen Family members.
太多沈家人的不甘
Searching for the truth of the incident
寻找当年的真相
has become my
成了我
only reason to live.
唯一活下去的理由
The world may have forgotten,
世人或许都已经忘记了
[or perhaps no one cares,]
或者说是无人在意
[but I remember clearly]
但我却清清楚楚地记得
and cannot forget for a moment
每时每刻都不敢忘
every innocent person
为沈家殉难的
who perished with the Shen Family.
每一个无辜的人
Not just you,
不是只有你
but also me.
还有我
I remember it well,
我记得
I have never forgotten Uncle Shen.
我从未忘记过沈伯伯
[When the Shen Family fell into misfortune,]
沈府出事
people said
人们说
that Uncle Shen had betrayed the empire
沈伯伯叛国通敌
I refused to believe it.
我不信
He was the most upright and selfless man
他是我见过
I have ever known,
最正直最无私的人
and he would never have committed an
绝不可能做出
act that harms the empire or its people.
伤国伤民之事
So from that moment on,
所以从那时起
I made a vow
我便立志
to become a female official
做女官
and enter the Ministry of Justice,
进刑部
hoping that one day
只求有朝一日
I could uncover the truth myself.
能自己找出真相
The world may call me The White Death
世人都叫我白无常
but I have come to accept
所以我也就认定了
that I am just a wandering soul.
自己就是个孤魂野鬼
I walk alone in this purgatory.
独自行走在这人间炼狱
I truly didn't expect that
真的没想到
there would be someone as foolish as me.
怎么会有人跟我一样傻
You are clearly warm,
明明是暖的
alive and vibrant,
活生生的
how could you be a wandering soul?
怎么会是孤魂野鬼呢
This heart
这颗心
is filled with
可是带着
the expectations of so many people.
那么多人的期待活着呢
From now on,
从今往后
you will no longer be alone.
你不会再是一个人
I will definitely strive
我一定会努力
to help you uncover the truth
帮你找出真相
and restore the honor of the Shens.
还沈府清白
Fetch the horse.
过去牵马去
My lord,
大阁领
[my lady,]
夫人
[you're finally back!]
你们可算回来了
Sorry to have caused you worry.
让你们担心了
My lady, take your time.
夫人莫急
I'm not eager at all...
我才没有着急呢
The ancestors of the Shen Family
沈家的列祖列宗
are surely watching over us.
在天有灵
My lord has finally seen the light!
大阁领现在悟了
Finally!
悟了
It's getting late now.
时辰不早了
My lady, you should get some sleep.
夫人早点休息
Alright.
好
Where are you going?
去哪儿
To sleep...
睡觉
There's a more
我与夫人
critical issue at hand.
有更重要的事情要办
Shen Du, I...
沈渡 我
You said it yourself
是你说过的
that I wouldn't
以后我不会
be alone anymore.
再是一个人
Since you've had the audacity to barge in my life,
既然有胆子闯进来
don't think you can easily get away.
以后可就逃不出去
I am Yan Xing.
我颜六娘
My word is my bond; once spoken,
一言既出
it cannot be taken back.
驷马难追
[Lord Zhang has arrived!]
张侍郎到
On behalf of Her Majesty,
太皇太后叫我来颁赏
I hereby reward Chief Clerk of the
赏刑部辖下都官主事
Ministry of Justice, Lady Yan Xing,
颜幸
[with ten thousand bolts of silk]
绸缎万匹
[and ten thousand taels of gold,]
黄金万两
[to recognize her meritorious service]
以显其功
and spread the royal grace!
广布恩泽
I am honored by the favor of Her Majesty.
谢太皇太后赏赐
Her Majesty has another decree.
太皇太后还有一旨
Her Majesty' decree states:
太皇太后有旨
the commander of Imperial Guard, Shen Du
今大内阁领沈渡
[has successfully quelled the rebellion]
平定叛乱
[and forged alliances with neighboring states,]
和协众邦
[demonstrating exceptional merit.]
功勋卓越
[In recognition of his contributions,]
考归万象
royal princess, Jia'an,
有皇女嘉安
[gentle and wise,]
柔佳居慧
[with grace and poise,]
婉嫕有仪
[conducting herself with elegance.]
行端仪雅
[She is well-versed in etiquette,]
礼教克娴
and now of marriageable age,
今及芳年
waiting in her royal chamber.
待字金闺
[The two are a match made by God.]
二人良缘天作
[By imperial decree, I approve their union.]
今下旨赐婚
[Let your unity strengthen the realm,]
望敬尽予国
[united in purpose.]
同心同德
[Lord Shen,]
大阁领
this is the decree of Her Majesty,
这是太皇太后的旨意
[not to be altered]
非是旁人的意志
[by others.]
可以左右
Accept it first and foremost.
好歹先把这旨接了再说
Lord Zhang has already seen it.
张侍郎也看到了
I have no intention
沈某无意
of marrying Princess Jia'an.
与嘉安郡主联姻
My beloved wife also
沈某的夫人
does not wish me to take another wife.
也不愿意沈某另娶
I hope you will convey this to Her Majesty.
还望回禀太皇太后
[Are you aware of the reason that Her]
你可知太皇太后
Majesty asked me to announce this decree?
为何让我来宣读这旨意
Such matters of reward
此等宣赏的事
[should be handled by]
应当是由
[the Ministry of Rites,]
太史局的人来做
so why was I sent in their stead?
何须用到我呢
Why is that?
为何
You fail to grasp,
你不懂
does Lord Shen also fail to comprehend?
大阁领还不懂吗
Please speak plainly
还请说个明白
and do not leave me guessing.
莫要与我打哑谜
[For the sake of Han Shiyuan]
看在韩世元
[who is now marrying into]
如今入赘
[your Yan Family,]
你们颜家的份上
[I will share this with you.]
我且透露给你
So that Shiyuan won't hold
免得以后让世元知道了
[a grudge against me.]
无端埋怨我
Think about it,
你想啊
Princess Jia'an is the most beloved
嘉安郡主是英王殿下
daughter of Princess Ying.
最疼爱的女儿
[And Princess Ying is]
而英王殿下又是
[Her Majesty' most cherished daughter.]
太皇太后最疼爱的公主
Princess Ying's temperament is very
英王殿下的性情
similar to that of Her Majesty,
又与太皇太后最为相似
which is why she receives the most favor,
所以获得了最多的宠爱
[even surpassing Prince Xian.]
甚至压过贤王一头
[In this context,]
此等状况下
[why bestow Princess Jia'an]
却将嘉安郡主
[upon Lord Shen]
赐予大阁领为平妻
as a primary wife?
为何意
[Lord Shen wields immense power,]
大阁领权势通天
[with exceptional achievements,]
功勋卓越
[and enjoys a status]
更有着一人之下
[that places him above all others.]
万人之上的尊贵荣华
He supervises all other officials.
可以举目四望
Yet, he stands alone,
可大阁领形单影只
with no support behind him.
背后没有任何的依靠
He has even
他更是
married you,
娶了你这个
a mere rank six official.
从六品的小吏为妻
[Even if Princess Jia'an wishes to marry,]
嘉安郡主她即便要嫁
[she should be able to choose freely among]
也应当在皇亲国戚当中
[the royal family.]
随意挑选
[Why must she marry Shen Du?]
何须嫁与沈渡
[Your father mentioned that]
你爹可说了
[now the Shen Family has only Shen Du left.]
如今沈家只余沈渡一人
The only ones still connected to the Shens
与沈家有关联的
are Mo Qianzhi and Zhong.
也只余莫谦之和那管家
[Mo Qianzhi has already passed away,]
莫谦之也已死
[so. in the imperial court,]
那沈渡在朝廷里面
[Shen Du is truly]
就真的是
[the most isolated individual.]
最无依无靠的一个人
[He also oversees all officials,]
又兼监察百官之职
[and any mistake he makes]
但凡出一点差错
[could easily lead to his downfall.]
那死也容易得很
[So, sacrifices are]
所以
necessary to catch your target.
舍不得孩子套不到狼
And Shen Du is the target.
沈渡便是那只狼
Lord Zhang,
张侍郎
I can bear whatever precautions
太皇太后如何防我
Her Majesty takes against me.
我都能忍
But a marriage decree is unnecessary.
但赐婚就不必了
I am already married.
沈某已娶妻
I will not marry again in this lifetime.
今生不会再娶了
Lord Zhang, I'm going to the palace to
张侍郎
plead with Her Majesty for reconsideration.
沈某现在随你回宫退婚
Shen Du...
沈渡
-Lord Shen! -Shen Du!
阁领 沈渡
Are you attempting to defy the decree?
你这是想抗旨不遵啊
Your Majesty,
太皇太后
I share a deep bond with my wife.
臣与夫人感情甚笃
Furthermore, I oversee the cabinet, and
何况臣执掌内阁
many officials harbor discontent against me.
监察百官多有怨言
This isn't a position of wealth and comfort,
实非富贵美差
and I do not wish for Princess Jia'an
更不愿嘉安郡主
to suffer by marrying me.
下嫁受苦
Princess Jia'an is not someone you
若非哀家撮合
could match without my assistance.
嘉安郡主岂是你能高攀
Princess Jia'an's distinguished lineage
嘉安郡主身份高贵
places her far above me,
臣自知不配
and I am too humble to even consider her.
更不敢觊觎
I implore Your Majesty to retract the decree.
还请太皇太后收回成命
You...
你
Insolence!
大胆
I've served the empire for many years and
臣为官数载
have never considered my own interests.
从未替自己惦念过什么
Only today,
唯独今日
I earnestly beseech Your Majesty.
恳请太皇太后收回成命
I will repay you with unwavering loyalty,
臣必定结草衔环
dedicating myself until my last breath!
鞠躬尽瘁死而后已
Lord Shen's loyalty has never faltered,
沈阁领一向忠心耿耿
his heart a reflection of his integrity.
其心可鉴
Your Royal Highness, please reconsider.
您一定要三思而后行
I understand,
臣知道
Your Majesty
太皇太后
is sincerely paving the way for me.
是苦心为臣铺路
I stand with a clear and sincere heart,
臣朗朗真心立于世
dedicated to easing your burdens.
一心为太皇太后分忧
If I need to marry Princess Jia'an
若还需要嘉安郡主下嫁
to secure my career path,
才得以保全
then it would suggest that Your Majesty
那便是太皇太后
does not have faith in my abilities.
信不过臣的能力
Your Majesty.
太皇太后
What is it now?
你又有什么事
Something happened at the Ming Hall!
明堂出事了
What?
什么
My men have performed numerous
臣派去的人曾查过多次
checks and uncovered no irregularities.
都未发现问题
But this time,
而这一次
their greed
是他们过于贪婪
led to mistakes,
而露出了破绽
which were finally caught.
刚好被察觉
[After my men went back to investigate,]
在倒回去查时
[they uncovered the problem.]
才发现问题所在
Someone had split the accounts into two ledgers.
有人分列了阴阳账本
Two ledgers?
阴阳账本
What are they exactly?
何为阴 何为阳
Regarding these two ledgers,
所谓阴阳
[one of them is an official ledger,]
便是明面上一本账册
[using the Longmen accounting method,]
用的是龙门记账法
but secretly,
而背地里
there is another ledger,
还有另一本账册
maintained with the Sijiao method.
用的却是四脚记账法
Continue.
继续
The official one
明面上的这本
which uses the Longmen method
龙门记账法记载的账册
reveals the artistry of the accountant.
做账的人手法巧妙
From the ledger,
从账本上看
indeed, no issues can be discerned.
的确不出任何差错
[Thus, since the founding of the Ming Hall,]
故而从明堂初建至如今
the officials responsible for the audits
审查的户部要员
have uncovered no issues.
查不出任何问题
The recently discovered
而刚刚发现的
other ledger
另一本账册
utilizes Sijiao method,
则用了四脚记账法
so at first glance,
所以打眼一看
it's difficult to detect any connection
察觉不出与明堂账册
with Ming Hall.
有任何相关
What is the discrepancy?
差了多少
[Outrageous!]
真是借了狗胆了
They truly have the audacity to embezzle
居然能贪墨
over twenty million taels of silver!
两千多万两白银啊
All officials involved in the
参与重建的官员
reconstruction are implicated,
无有不涉及
except for Lord Zhang Baohuan.
除却张宝环张大人
Baohuan is not adept at accounting
宝环对此账目并不擅长
[and lacks the boldness.]
也无此胆量
However,
但是
Ming Hall
这明堂之事
was entrusted to him for oversight,
是交付于他统筹的
[so he's to blame for poor oversight.]
他便有监察不力之罪
Relieve him of his duties.
让他走
Let him retire for convalescence.
去往别院精心静养吧
Yes.
是
As for the others...
至于其他人
These officials
这些官员
belong to various factions...
位列朝中各个党派
Various factions?
各个党派
Even my Zhou Family?
还有我周氏一族
All of this is merely my conjecture.
微臣臆说
Please forgive my insolence!
还望太皇太后恕罪
You are not to blame.
你何罪之有啊
I thought that although
我只当
[the officials have their own agendas,]
朝中官员虽各怀心思
[they all care for the empire.]
但都心系天下
I never thought catastrophe
却万万没有想到
would start from such small beginnings.
这毒瘤起于微末呀
[Now,]
如今是
the undercurrents are surging,
暗影浮动
and hearts are difficult to read.
人心难测
Your Majesty is devoted to the empire,
太皇太后一心为国
yet the officials each
而朝中大臣
harbor their own agendas,
却个个别有心思
particularly following the suicide of
尤其
the governor of Yingzhou province,
是营州刺史
Mo Qianzhi.
莫谦之一事后
With the position in the Gannan vacant,
甘南道尚未有人接任
it seems they
我看
are all getting impatient.
他们都有些等不及了
It's time to give them a stern warning!
是时候敲打一番了
Your Majesty,
太皇太后
Personal interactions between Imperial
沈渡的内卫府
Guard and other offices are infrequent,
鲜少与他人走动
and Shen Du is diligent in his duties.
办事也尽心尽力
He'd be a good candidate for investigation.
会是个不错的人选
[However,]
只是
[if he marries Princess Jia'an,]
若他与嘉安郡主结亲
it might complicate
那恐怕往后做事
his work in the future.
就多有掣肘了
You want to help him out of trouble,
你想帮他
but you must see if he is clever enough.
也得看看他够不够聪明
Regarding Ming Hall,
明堂一事
do not make it public yet;
先不要声张
investigate discreetly.
暗查
Understood.
是
Issue my decrees separately to
御察司
the Imperial Inspectorate
内卫府
and the Imperial Guard.
分别传我的旨令
You truly fear nothing.
你倒真是什么都不怕
I had expected to at least
原本以为
endure some corporal punishment,
难免一顿皮肉之苦
but it was less arduous than I had thought.
没想到比想象中顺利些
Are you suggesting that the
你是说
annulment of the decree was achieved?
退婚之事就这么过去了
Not necessarily.
未必
Her Majesty
太皇太后这口恶气
has yet to vent her anger.
还没有出呢
The marriage decree came suspiciously,
但赐婚一事来得蹊跷
and it likely ties back to that booklet.
恐怕与那本册子有关
Princess Ying must be anxious about
想必是英王殿下
my potential disclosure of her
怕我将她
financial backing for the Ying troops,
资助营州兵一事呈上
leading her to enlist Her Majesty
所以才让太皇太后赐婚
to bind me with a marriage.
想要将我绊住
But unfortunately, Her Royal Highness
但可惜
is preoccupied with other matters.
太皇太后无暇顾及此事
Is it the issue related to Ming Hall?
是明堂那边出了大事
Did you know about this all along?
你早就知道此事
Shen Du,
沈渡
could it be that
难道说
Lady Xu's report on this was not
徐内司刚好上报此事
a mere coincidence?
并非碰巧
People are unaware
人们不知道
that the Ming Hall holds deep significance
明堂对于太皇太后来说
for Her Majesty.
另有深意
It symbolizes the affection between
它是见证了太皇太后
Her and the late emperor.
与先帝的情意之所
After the fire at the Ming Hall,
明堂大火之后
Her Majesty has been deeply
太皇太后对于重建之事
concerned about the reconstruction.
极为上心
Not only did she appoint
不仅派去了
her most trusted
自己极为信任的
Zhang Baohuan to oversee it,
张宝环坐镇
but she also issued a decree that there
还下旨
would be no limit on the renovation funds.
修缮经费上不封顶
No limit?
上不封顶
Unlimited funds
经费无上限
does not mean that the corrupt officials
不代表底下蛀虫
can fill their pockets.
可以中饱私囊
How many people are implicated?
那涉及了多少啊
It's possible to destabilize the imperial court.
恐怕可以撼动整个朝堂
They have truly infuriated
他们算是彻底激怒了
Her Majesty.
太皇太后